[MUSIC]
效果量：相關係數
In this lecture, we'll continue talking about the effect sizes, but
這一講繼續談效果量
now we'll focus on the R family of effect size measures.
主角是相關係數一類的效果量
These include correlations, but also effect size measures for
除了相關係數，還有變異數分析的效果量
像是eta平方
ANOVA such as eta squared.
除了相關係數，還有變異數分析的效果量
像是eta平方
Now, if we look into the scientific literature,
我們從科學文獻裡找到這個例子來做介紹
there's an example of an effect that can be describe by a correlation.
Namely, the Chocolate Consumption in a country is related
這篇論文談論一國的巧克力消費量與獲得諾貝爾獎的關係
to the amount of Nobel Prizes that are won.
Lets take a look at the data,
看看論文裡的資料
we can plot the amount of the Nobel Prize laureates on one axis.
這張圖的縱軸是諾貝爾獎得主人數
The amount of chocolate that's eaten in a country in the other axis and
橫軸是國內巧克力消費量
there we see a strong positive correlation.
兩者有很強的正相關(0.79)
In this case,
首先聲明
I don't want to discuss how correlation does not imply causation, that's obvious.
我不想用這麼明顯的例子重申相關不等於因果
But here I just want to point at the size of the effect.
只是藉此說明效果量大小的解讀關鍵
As I mentioned before, it's very important to always interpret effect size and
如上一講所提，達0.8的效果量算是很高
in this case a correlation of 0.8 is huge.
必須小心地推測其中意義
Such a big effect that that alone should make you wonder whether this is real
特別是這樣的案例讓人不得不懷疑資料的真偽
data or not.
Now if you look at correlations, we can again specify benchmarks for
相關係數類的效果量也有一套小中大判斷標準
small, medium and large effect sizes.
A small correlation of
0.1 as visualized here,
最小的效果量0.1，資料散佈如這張圖顯示
again we're using the visualizations
from R Psychologist, great website.
和上一講相同，都是取自R Psycholgist網站
Where you can play around with different visualizations for all sorts of basic
你可以用網站的視覺化工具了解
statistical concept such as
correlations and other effect sizes.
相關與各類效果量的統計概念
So this is what the correlation of 0.1 looks like.
相關係數0.1的資料分佈大致像這樣
A correlation that's medium.
這是相關係數的中效果量
A medium effect size is a correlation of 0.3, visualized here as well.
相關係數至少是0.3才算中效果量，
如這張圖的分佈
In a large correlation, a benchmark is set to 0.5.
相關係數至少是0.5才算大效果量
Now correlations range from zero, no effect,
相關係數的數值範圍包括0
there's no relation between two variables.
代表變項之間沒有關係或無效果
To either minus one,
也包括-1
a perfect negative correlation,
to plus one, perfect positive correlation.
代表絕對負相關
或是+1，代表絕對正相關
If you want to get a feel for
想要增加自已對相關性的感受
視覺化是不錯的方法
what's correlations look like if you visualize them.
想要增加自已對相關性的感受
視覺化是不錯的方法
I can really recommend this website guessthecorrelation.com where they have
我真摰推薦這個網站guessthecorrelation.com
game of fights recognizing effect size measures.
透過玩遊戲了解相關係數的效果量
And if you play around with this website,
玩過幾輪之後
you'll get a better understanding of what different effect sizes look like.
你會更了解相關係數數值與效果量大小
Now previously we talked about the Cohen's D measure of effect size.
前一講談使用Cohen's d測量效果量
Both Cohen's D and correlations can be used to calculate meta analysis.
而相關係數和Cohen's d一樣都可以做整合分析
Therefore, it might not be very surprising that you can calculate the Cohen's D
所以不必驚訝Cohen's d可以轉換成Cohen's r
into a Cohen's R.
You can convert the one into the other,
運用這個公式
this is the formula that you might use for this.
兩種數值可以相互轉換
Again, I'm not going to go into too much detail about this specific formula.
同樣地，在此我不會仔細解釋公式的細節
But I just want to point out that it's possible to convert
只是指出不同種類的效果量是可以彼此互換的
one effect size into the other effect size.
And there are different spreadsheets online if you want to accomplish this.
也有讓你做轉換的網路資源可使用
Now in ANOVA's or regressions, we don't really use the simple correlation but we
在變異數分析或迴歸的場合
通常不會使用相關係數
used R squared or for ANOVA, eta squared, omega squared and epsilon squared.
而是用這張投影片上方四種效果量
This effect size measures that express the proportion of
這些效果量呈現測得的真實效果變異
the total variance that's explained by an effect.
佔總變異的比例
R squared and eta squared are slightly biased effect size estimators.
R平方與eta平方是真實效果量的有偏誤估計值
And omega squared and epsilon squared are less biased.
別外兩種估計值的偏誤較少
In this case, they are not perfectly unbiased, but they are pretty close.
雖然不是完全不偏，但已經相當接近
It turns out that epsilon squared is least biased effect size measure.
其中最不偏的估計值是epsilon平方
Although omega squared is more often used and more widely recommended.
雖然其中最常用的是Omega平方
Okada, 2013 suggests that this
2013年岡田謙介發表的論文指出
difference might be due to a faulty random number generator in one of the original
原始論文的差異若是來自錯誤的隨機數值
papers that compared these different effect sizes.
很可能導致效果量的估計偏誤
I thought this was funny to point out that even in this kind of simulation work,
這篇論文的有趣之處是即使是模擬研究
you can have reproducibility problems based on faulty random number generators.
使用不良的隨機數值生產方法也會導致重製性問題
It doesn't matter too much, you can used both omega squared and epsilon squared.
不關這個問題有多嚴重，
建議同時呈現omega平方與eplsilon平方
The difference between the two is actually quite small.
在一般情況，兩者的差異並不大
Now conceptually, this effect size measures answer a simple question.
這些效果量的測量都是要回答一個簡單問題
How much does the relationship between x and y reduce the error in the data?
變項x與y的關係要多高，才能減除資料裡的誤差？
Let's try to visualize this.
我們用視覺化說明這個問題
On the left you can see a model where there is no relationship
左圖的線性模型表示兩個變項之間沒有關係
between the two variables.
There's a horizontal line if there's an increase in one variable,
因為水平線的變項數值增加
there is zero increase in the other variable.
另一個變項並無增加
Now we can calculate the sum of squares in this model where there's
把圖上每一對相對於變項間無關係的數值
no relationship between the two variables.
計算數值的平方和
And the red squares indicates the sum of squares.
如圖中的紅色方塊區域所示
So this is the total sum of squares if there's no relationship
這塊面積也是兩變項間的總平方和
between the two variables.
On the right, we allow for
在右邊的圖
the model to have a relationship between the two variables.
是兩個變項有關係的線性模型
Now if there is an increase in one variable,
其中一個變項的數值增加
we see there is also an increase in the other variable.
另一個變項的數值也隨之增加
We again calculate the sum of squares, now indicated by the blue squares.
同樣計算平方和，正如藍色方塊面積所示
This is the sum of squares of the residuals.
代表殘差的平方和
And R squared is simply the sum of squares of the residuals divided by
R平方正是殘差的平方和除以總平方和
the total sum of squares.
Now if we use effect sizes for power analysis,
用這種效果量做檢定力分析
you'll see that most statistical software asks for Cohen's f.
像G Power需要計算Cohen's f的資訊
Cohen's f can simply be calculated from eta squared
Cohens' f可使用eta平方
using the formula that's on the screen here.
代入投影片左側的公式計算得出
You can also use statistical software to calculate Cohen's f from eta squared.
而G Power也有計算Cohen's f的功能
A screenshot from G power, free statistical software, is on the right.
如何在G Power呼叫這個視窗，請參考本週作業
Now it's important to recognize that if you want to calculate Cohen's
這張投影片示範如何使用G Power
整合效果量和Cohen's f
f within subject design and
這張投影片示範如何使用G Power
整合效果量和Cohen's f
you're using G power, there's something you need to keep in mind.
計算受試者內設計的樣本數
In within subject designs, G power expects a different version of partial
G Power計算受試者內設計的效果量數值
是以特別公式計算partial eta平方
eta squared than statistical software such as SPSS or R would provide.
而其他統計軟體像SPSS和R
是用另一種公式計算
Now this is great free software, so I'm not complaining.
因為G Power很好用，我對此不予置評
But for some weird reason, these researchers expect
只是有研究者會基於各種理由
a different default than most other statistical software.
希望採用某種軟體的計算結果
This is only a situation if you use power calculations within designs.
受試者內設計的考驗力是各軟體計算差異最大的狀況
In these situations, if you want to directly input eta squared,
如果有需要，你可以在G Power直接輸入
其他軟體計算的partial eta平方
you need to click on the option box that's available on the screen.
在你的G Power視窗中
點選像這個示範截圖的Options按鈕
And if you click in this option box, then you get a specific menu
接著會跳出這個特別選單
where you can say, I want to input partial eta squared as in SPSS.
你可以在選單上選擇要用SPSS的算法
Also if you use different types of software such as R,
如果你要用R的算法
then this is the option that you want to choose.
也是選同樣的選項
If you forget to highlight this option,
如果你沒有調整選項
then the power calculations might be off quite considerably.
考驗力的計算就照G Power預設執行
Now very often in experimental designs,
在許多實驗設計案例裡
you're interested in the partial variance explained by only one factor.
有興趣的通常只有一個因素能解釋的部份變異
For example, a factor that you manipulated.
例如研究者操作的變項
In these situations, you will calculate partial eta squared or again,
這時候可以計算partial eta平方
the less biased partial omega squared or partial epsilon squared.
或者估計值比較不偏的另外兩種
Now in a one-way ANOVA, eta squared is identical to partial eta squared.
單因子變異數分析的eta平方等於partial eta平方
So if you're a little bit lazy, you don't have to report this small p,
如果想省點編輯工作，可以不必把下標p打出來
you don't have to type it in.
It's easier just to say eta squared in this situations.
單因子設計都直接稱呼eta平方
Cohen has provided benchmarks to define small, medium and large Cohen's fs.
Cohen也貼心提供Cohen's f大小判斷標準
Cohen's f of 0.1 is small, 0.25 is medium and 0.5 is considered the large effect.
小效果下限0.1，中效果0.25，大效果0.5
Now we can use the formula that we saw earlier to calculate Cohen's f
還有公式能輕鬆將eta平方等數值轉換成Cohen's f
from eta squared or vice-versa.
And then we can also create benchmarks for
所以可知eta平方的判斷標準是
eta squared that are small, 0.0099, medium,
小效果至少0.0099
0.0588, and large, 0.1379.
中效果0.0588，大效果0.1379
Now this is a lot of digits and this is precision that's not really warranted.
雖然小數點後數字很多，但是不必太精確比較
But this is a consequence of directly converting
這些數字只是從Cohen's f直接轉換過來的結果
the effect sizes that Cohen used into eta squared.
Now Cohen talks about eta squared when he defines these benchmarks.
要注意的是
Cohen訂出判斷標準時，表面上說是eta平方
But he actually means partial eta squared.
實際是指partial eta平方
So you should use these benchmarks for partial eta squared, not for
所以這項判斷標準要用在partial eta平方
eta squared itself.
而非eta平方
Another important thing to keep in mind.
請務必記住
Nowadays we also see more novel versions of eta squared.
現在還可以使用另一種eta平方
And one very useful one, which removes this difference between within and
並且這一種是受試者間與受試者內設計通用
between subject effect sizes.
And can generalize between within and between subject designs
這麼好用的效果量稱為通用化eta平方
is generalized eta squared, developed by Olejnik and Algina.
由Olenjink與Algina提出
Now I just want to point out that this exists.
這種效果量我不細談如何計算
If you're interested in reporting effect sizes or if you use the statistical
如果你有興趣使用這種效果量做報告
software that automatically provides these generalized eta squared values.
或者想知道有什麼軟體可以計算
They're very useful and might be the best to report.
可以參考原始論文，並且最好在你的報告裡引用
In this lecture, we talked about the R family of effect sizes.
這一講介紹相關係數一類的效果量
Which allow you to quantify the degree of association between two variables.
可計量變項之間的關聯強度
I pointed out some peculiarities when you used eta squared in within
我特別指出使用G Power計算受試者內設計的eta平方
subject designs when you perform power calculations in G power.
應該留意的設定與研究需要的差別
And provided some benchmarks that you can use to interpret these effect sizes if you
還有提供一些這類效果量的大小判斷標準
report them in your result section.
做為你的報告寫作參考
[MUSIC]
影片結束